A Guide to the Robert R. Gilruth Papers, 1936-1989
Special Collections, Virginia Tech
Special Collections, Virginia Tech
Robert R. Gilruth Papers, 1936-1989
Special Collections, Virginia Tech, Blacksburg, Va.
Ms1990-053
6.6 cu. ft. 6 boxes; 7 oversize folders
The collection consists of Robert R. Gilruth's papers, notes, records, articles, photographs, awards, degrees, certificates, and artifacts from 1936-1989.
Gilruth, Robert R., (Robert Rowe), 1913-
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
Collection is open for research.
Acquisition Information
The Robert R. Gilruth Papers were donated to Special Collections in multiple accessions during 1990 and 1994.
Biographical Note
Robert R. Gilruth (1913-2000) was an aerospace engineer and NACA/NASA administrator. He received his B.S. in aeronautical engineering from the University of Minnesota (1935), as well as his M.S. (1936). Gilruth was also a flight research engineer for Langley Aeronautical Laboratory of the National Advisory Committee for Aeronautics (1937-1945). From 1945 to 1950, he worked as chief of the Pilotless Aircraft Research Division, and assistant director (1950-58). He headed the Space Task Group for NASA (1958-61), and was charged with directing Project Mercury. From 1961 to 1972, he was the first director of the NASA Manned Spacecraft Center (MSC) in Houston.
The NASA website has a number of more extensive resources on Gilruth's work, including interviews and press releases, discoverable by going to the site and searching "Gilruth."
Scope and Content
The collection consists of Robert R. Gilruth's papers, notes, records, articles, photographs, awards, degrees, certificates, and artifacts. A majority of the collection contains professional papers from Gilruth's work in NACA and NASA, including speeches and presentations, reports, photographs, oral history transcripts, notes, and newpapersclippings, as well as certificates, awards, and artifacts. Personal materials include a typescript diary, Gilruth's 1936 M.S. Thesis, and an unpublished memoir. A small collection of books has been removed and cataloged for the Rare Book Collection at Special Collections.
Arrangement
Materials in the collection are in their original physical order. Newspaper clippings and oversize materials were removed from boxes and are located in flat files. The contents list below shows the collection grouped by subject or material type into nine series, arranged alphabetically by series title.
Series I: Artifacts includes awards and other objects collected by or given to Gilruth during his career. Series II: Awards, Certificates, and Degrees, contains a variety of certificates marking Gilruth's achievements, degrees, and memberships to organizations. Series III: Correspondence includes primarily incoming professional letters and telegrams received by Gilruth. Series IV: Interviews and Memoirs consists of transcripts and memoirs relating to Gilruth and other aeronautics professionals. Series V: Lectures and Speeches contains texts and drafts of speeches given by Gilruth. Series VI: Newspaper Clippings includes a variety of complete newspapers and specific articles about or collected by Gilruth. Series VII: Personal Papers consists of diaries, itineraries, writings, and other personal materials. Series VIII: Photographs contains photographs of professional projects, including Gemini and Apollo missions, as well as images of colleagues and NASA locations. Series VIIII: Reports, Notes, and Professional Writings consists of writing created by Gilruth during his career, notes, research articles, and subject files.
Adjunct Descriptive Data
Separated Materials
The following books were removed to the rare book collection:
Spacewatch, Screening Copy/27:40 (Video Cassette)
Shaping Tomorrow, NASA-Langley 70th Anniversary, 17 July 1987 (Video Cassette)
Gemini Program, Ivan D. Ertel
This Was Air Travel, Henry R. Palmer, Jr.
10:56:20PM EDT 7/20/69, CBS News over CBS Television Network
Arizona Highways, Raymond Carlson
Men of Space, Shirley Thomas
Frontiers of Astronomy, Fred Hoyle
Model Research: The National Advisory Committee for Aeronautics 1915-1958, Volumes 1 & 2, Alex Roland
Biomedical Results from Skylab, Richard S. Johnston and Lawrence F. Dietlein
Wind Tunnels of NASA, Donald D. Baals and William R. Corliss
The Moon Book, Bevan M. French
A Continent for Science: The Antarctic Adventure, Richard S. Lewis
Engineer in Charge, James R. Hansen
Managing NASA in the Apollo Era, Arnold S. Levine
Index Terms
Subjects:
Archives of American Aerospace Exploration (AAAE); Project Apollo (U.S.); Project Gemini (U.S.); Science and Technology; United States. National Aeronautics and Space Administration
Occupations:
Aerospace engineers; United States. National Aeronautics and Space Administration--Officials and employees
Contents List
- Series I: Artifacts
  - NASA Flag (N.D.) (Box-folder 3-41)
  - Membership pin inscribed "National Congress of Parents and Teachers 1897" (Box 6)
  - Medal for winning the "News Tribune Miniature Aircraft Tournament 1929" (Box 6)
  - Commemorative red ribbon with commemorative pin inscribed "Mercury Orbital, Friendship 7" [c. 1963] (Box 6)
  - Commemorative object from the NASA-Ames Research Center (Box 6)
  - Commendation Medal for Outstanding Achievements from the University of Minnesota (Box 6)
  - Commemorative object inscribed "Authentic Silver Re-Strike 1768 Spanish Pillar Dollar Presented to Dr. Robert R. Gilruth, Southwestern Savings Association New Home Office Dedication, Houston, Texas, September, 1968" (Box 6)
- Series II: Awards, Certificates, and Degrees
  - Skin Diving Diploma from Southwest Council of Skin Diving Clubs for Mrs. E. Jean Gilruth (1968) (Box-folder 3-29)
  - President's Award for Distinguished Federal Service - 1962 (Box-folder 3-27)
  - Master of Science in Aeronautical Engineering from University of Minnesota (1936) (Box-folder 3-31)
  - Bachelor of Aeronautical Engineering from University of Minnesota for Robert R. Gilruth (1935) (Box-folder 3-32)
  - Bachelor of Aeronautical Engineering from University of Minnesota for Ester Jean Barnhill (1935) (Box-folder 3-33)
  - Citation for Houston Manned Spacecraft Center for Moon Landing Efforts from Rockefeller Public Service awards (1969) (Box-folder 3-34)
  - Certificate of Appreciation, National Research Council, Aeronautics and Space Engineering Board (1981) (Box-folder 3-35)
  - Rockefeller Public Service Award for Distinguished Service, Princeton University (1969) (Box-folder 3-36)
  - Honrary Doctorate from George Washington Univ. (1962); Newsclipping and Letter (Box-folder 3-39)
  - Honorary Fellow, American Institute of Aeronautics and Astronautics Certificate and Letter (1962) (Box-folder 3-38)
  - Honorary Citizen of Roswell, N. M. (Key to the City) (Box 5)
  - Recognition Plaque from Space Industries International (Box 5)
  - Honorary Degree from New Mexico State University (Box 5)
  - Spirit of St. Louis Medal 1964 (The American Society of Mechanical Engineers) (Box 5)
  - ASME Medal 1970 (The American Society of Mechanical Engineers) (Box 5)
  - Honorary Degree from Michigan College of Mining and Technology (Box 5)
  - Recognition of Outstanding Achievement from the Regents of the University of Minnesota (Box 5)
  - Citation for Distinguished and Exceptional Service from the Mayor of the City of New York (Box 5)
  - Honorary Degree from the George Washington University (Box 5)
  - Certificates from the Institute of the Aeronautical Sciences (elected honorary fellow and fellow) (Box 5)
  - Honorary Degree from the University of Minnesota (Box 5)
  - Award from AIAA (Honorary Fellow) (Box 5)
  - Certificate of Membership, Internationalis Astronautica Academia (Folder 6)
  - Sylvanus Albert Reed Award, Institute of the Aeronautical Sciences (Folder 6)
  - Honorary Degree, Doctor of Science, Indiana Institute of Technology, 1962 (Folder 6)
  - Membership Certificate, National Academy of Sciences of the United States of America, 1974 (Folder 6)
  - Certificate of Appreciation, NASA, 1977 (Folder 6)
  - Distinguished Service Medal (Apollo 8), NASA, 1969 (Folder 6)
  - Distinguished Service Medal (Apollo Program), NASA, 1969 (Folder 6)
  - Certificate of Recognition, Duluth Central High School, 1962 (Folder 6)
  - H. Res. 487, Recognition (Apollo 11) from the U. S. House of Representatives, 1969 (Folder 6)
  - National Academy of Engineering Diploma, 1968 (Folder 6)
  - National Air and Space Museum, Outstanding Achievement in Aerospace Technology, 1985 (Folder 6)
  - Louis W. Hill Space Transportation Award, 1961 (Folder 6)
  - Honorary Fellow Certificate, Royal Aeronautical Society, 1969 (Folder 6)
- Series III: Correspondence
  - Low/Mcdivitt Correspondence (2 folders) (Box-folder 1-17 to 1-18)
  - Letters of Congratulations (Box-folder 1-19)
  - Letters and Telegrams -- 1968-1971 (Box-folder 1-20)
- Series IV: Interviews and Memoirs
  - Oral History Transcript -- Interview with R. R. Gilruth on Gemini Program - 1968 (Box-folder 4-19)
  - "Notes on Interview with Milton W. Rosen at NASA HQ, Washington, 14 November 1969" (Box-folder 4-20)
  - Oral History Transcript -- Interview with R. R. Gilruth on NASA History - 1969 (Box-folder 4-21)
  - "The Director of MSC -- Excerpt from MSC Historical Interview with Geaorge M. Low" (c.a. 1970) (Box-folder 4-23)
  - "Memoir: from Wallops Island to Mercury, 1945-1958" (c.a. 1970) (Box-folder 4-24)
  - "United States Manned Space Flight, 1960-1970" (for use by mandatory publishing company encyclopedia yearbook) (Box-folder 4-25)
  - "Transcript of Tape Made by Messrs, Gilruth, Lunney, Johnson, and Hardy Following Their Trip to Moscow, 23-29 October 1970" (Box-folder 4-26)
  - Oral History Transcript -- Interview with R. R. Gilruth on Apollo Program - 1973 (Box-folder 4-30)
  - Oral History Transcript -- Interview with R. R. Gilruth on Skylab Program - 1975 (Box-folder 4-33)
  - Manuscript notes for a memoir (n.d.) (Box-folder 4-36)
  - Memorandum for Record: Telcon Interview (Eugene Emme) - 1975 (Box-folder 4-32)
- Series V: Lectures and Speeches
  - "Investiture '92" (Box-folder 3-28)
  - "Space Heros Get 'Missed' College Credit" (1962) (Box-folder 3-30)
  - Address to the Rice University Associates - 1963 (Box-folder 4-14)
  - Commencement Address to Michigan College of Mining and Technology - 1963 (Box-folder 4-15)
  - Speech at Macalester College: "The Manned Space Flight Program - A Progess Report" - 1964 (Box-folder 4-16)
  - Unidentified Speech Marked "Draft" - 1964 (Box-folder 4-17)
  - Commencement Address to Hancock High School, Hancock, Michigan - 1970 (Box-folder 4-22)
  - "To the Moon and Beyond" (Wright Memorial Lecture) c.a. 1971 (Box-folder 4-28)
  - "Farewell Speech Notes" (as Director of MSC) March 3, 1972 (Box-folder 4-29)
  - "Address to the Special Session" - c.a. 1975 (Box-folder 4-31)
  - "Wings Club Speech" (c.a. 1976) (Box-folder 4-34)
- Series VI: Newspaper Clippings
  - Newspaper Clippings RE: Receipt of NASA's Distinguished Service Medal (1962) (Box-folder 3-26)
  - Oversize Clippings and Full Newspapers (5 folders) (Folder 1-5)
- Series VII: Personal Papers
  - Books (Box-folder 2-17)
  - Currency (Box-folder 3-25)
  - Commencement Programs (Box-folder 3-40)
  - Typescript Diary, February 10 - March 3, 1961 (Box-folder 4-13)
  - Typescript Diary, May 8-22, 1967 (Box-folder 4-18)
  - Itinerary for a Trip to Moscow, Nov. 26 - Dec. 9, 1971 (Box-folder 4-27)
  - Henry Dethloff, Draft of a History of Johnson Space Center - 1989 (Box-folder 4-35)
- Series VIII: Photographs
  - Dedication of Recreation Center (Photographs) - 1973 (Box-folder 2-2)
  - Photographs -- Apollo 12 - 1969 (Box-folder 2-19)
  - Photographs (Box-folder 2-20)
  - Photographs -- Apollo 15 (Box-folder 2-21)
  - Key to Photos from Space (Box-folder 3-1)
  - Photographs (6 folders) (Box-folder 3-2 to 3-7)
  - Project Mercury Photographs -- 1960s (3 folders) (Box-folder 3-8 to 3-10)
  - Photographs -- Apollo 10 - 1969 (Box-folder 3-11)
  - Photographs (Box-folder 3-12)
  - Photographs -- L.B.J.'s Visit to Center (1965-1968) (Box-folder 3-13)
  - Photographs -- Apollo Spacecraft and Operations (general) (Box-folder 3-14)
  - Photographs -- Russians at MSC - 1971 (Box-folder 3-15)
  - Photographs -- Gemini - 1965 (Box-folder 3-16)
  - Photographs -- Goddard Museum (Box-folder 3-17)
  - Photographs -- Dr. Gilruth and Jerry Warrenburg (Box-folder 3-18)
  - Photographs -- JSC - Pictures of Facilities (1965-1973) (Box-folder 3-19)
  - Photographs -- Apollo 14 and Moon (Box-folder 3-20)
  - Photographs -- Royalty - 1967 (Box-folder 3-21)
  - Photgraphs -- Distinguished People (1960's-1970's) (Box-folder 3-22)
  - Photographs -- Apollo - Suyz Negotiations and J.S.C. (Box-folder 3-23)
  - Guest List and Photographs of Earth (1970's) (Box-folder 3-24)
  - Oversize Photographs and Small Artworks (Folder 7)
- Series VIIII: Reports, Notes, and Professional Writings
  - Drafts - Chapters 10, 11, and unknown (Box-folder 2-1)
  - Reports and Articles (4 folders) (Box-folder 1-1 to 1-4)
  - Apollo Notes -- #1 Apr. - July '67 (Box-folder 1-5)
  - Apollo Notes -- #2 Aug. - Dec. '67 (2 folders) (Box-folder 1-6 to 1-7)
  - Apollo Notes -- #3 Jan. - Mar. '68 (Box-folder 1-8)
  - Apollo Notes -- #4 Apr. - July '68 (2 folders) (Box-folder 1-9 to 1-10)
  - Apollo Notes -- #5 Aug. 1 - Dec. 31, '68 (3 folders) (Box-folder 1-11 to 1-13)
  - Apollo Notes -- #6 Jan. 1 - Apr. 30, '69 (2 folders) (Box-folder 1-14 to 1-15)
  - Apollo Notes -- 4/30 - 11/5/69 (Box-folder 1-16)
  - Reports and Articles (14 folders) (Box-folder 2-3 to 2-16)
  - Miscellaneous (Box-folder 2-18)
  - "R.A.E. News. The Journal of the Royal Aircraft Establishment" Vol. 24 No. 3 (1971) (Box-folder 3-37)
  - "The Effect of Wing-Tip Propellers on the Aerodynamic Charateristics of a Low Aspect Ratio Wing" (MS Thesis, U. Minnesota) - 1936 (Box-folder 4-1)
  - "An Investigation of the Lift and Thrust Theoretically Available from the Angular Momentum of a Propeller Wake" - c.a. 1938 (Box-folder 4-2)
  - "Notes on the Stalling of Vertical Trail Surfaces and on FIN Design" -- F. L. Thonpson and R. R. Gilruth - 1940 (Box-folder 4-3)
  - "Analysis and Prediction of Longitudinal Stability of Airplanes" -- R. R. Gilruth and M. D. White - 1941 (Box-folder 4-4)
  - "Lateral Control Required for Satisfactory Flying Qualities..." -- R. R. Gilruth and W. N. Turner - 1941 (Box-folder 4-5)
  - "Lateral Control Required for Satisfactory Flying Qualities..." -- R. R. Gilruth and W. N. Turner (NACA Report No. 715) - 1941 (Box-folder 4-6)
  - "Requirements for Satisfactory Flying Qualities of Airplanes" (1941) (Box-folder 4-7)
  - "Requirements for Satisfactory Flying Qualities of Airplanes" (NACA Wartime Report) - 1941 (Box-folder 4-8)
  - "Requirements for Satisfactory Flying Qaulities of Airplanes" (NACA Report No. 755) - 1943 (Box-folder 4-9)
  - "Analysis of Vertical-Tail Loads in Rolling Pull-Out Maneuvers" - 1944 (Box-folder 4-10)
  - "Aerodynamic Problems of Guided Missiles" - 1947 (Box-folder 4-11)
  - "Resume and Analysis of NACA Wing-Flow Tests" (1947-1948) (Box-folder 4-12)